係。
裝唔係你好。
講咗啲舊都得。
因為我變咗咧。
誒，睇有冇其他提名。
好。
呢度我使唔使講呢啲啊？
誒，要請你嚟一嚟先啦嚇。
我淨係請佢揀架得啦。
哦，冇就阿陳建波主席當任主席。O.K.
阿陳振英議員，誒，我提名你啊，阿陳建波議員做翻主席，唔該。
妖冇嘅，係係係唔好意思，因為咧而家啲一係提名，我你要上翻嚟誒。
O.K.噉啊，有冇人係和議？係阿姚思明議員和議嚇。O.K.噉我都自立提名嘅。咁仲有冇其他提名？
須由一名委員口頭作出，並須由最少另外一名委員咧口頭賦予嘅，並獲得提名嘅委員支持。而家請委員提名。
大家係咪要考唔考慮選呢個副主席咧？啊，冇需要係嘛？OK，好噉，現在咧，我哋誒請當局進場啊嘛。
各位同事早晨啊！而家夠鍾又夠法定人數啊！現在進行咧係二零一八年山頂纜車安全修訂條例生效公告日期公告小組委員會嘅主席嘅選舉。咁咧呢個根據我哋內務守則嘅規定咧，而家請委員提名一個主席嘅人選，有效提名咧。
needed to upgrade the peak tram.
and in all types of weather.
啊，孫萬天先生啊，OK。
等佢講唔識，講完先。好。
係誒，多謝主席，早晨各位，嗯。
呢個咧係落實山頂纜車優化發展計劃嘅最後一步嚟嘅。
Good morning. Thank you very much for inviting us to the meeting today.
車車廂可載乘客數目上限增至咧二百一十人嘅實施日期。
Maybe I can start by reminding everyone why why we.
There were very long waiting times for passengers, up to two hours during busy holiday periods.
Prior to 2019， we had very long queues forming outside the the peak tram termini on most weekends and and certainly public holidays.
立法會咧對修訂規例咧並無異議嘅，當時立法會亦同意咧有關規例嘅實施日期咧係由商務及經濟發展局局長以憲報公告指定。
如果議議員都冇議主席同議員都冇異議嘅話，我而家請山頂纜車有限公司代表向議員交代發展計劃嘅最新發展進展。好啊，係咪啊？曾英美女士係咪？係邊位交代？係佢。
好啊！各位在席嘅官員咧，大家睇個名單已經喺度啦。噉我唔再介紹啦。噉我而家首先請誒政府當局咧向委員簡介呢一條誒條例啦。噉啊，然後請委員提問嘅嚇，請政府當。
政府咧喺今年誒七月九日咧喺誒憲報刊登咗二零一八年《山頂纜車括弧安全括弧修訂規例》括弧生效日期公告喺呢個公告裏邊咧，商務及經濟發展局局長指定今年二零二一年嘅十二月十七日為山頂纜。
本屆嘅立法會咧，其實已經喺二零一八年十月同埋十一月咧，聽取咗我哋政府同埋山頂纜車有限公司交代優化發展計劃嘅詳情，以及將纜車車廂載客量增加至二百一十名乘客而作出嘅誒修訂規例。
所以，我們。
as we previously presented.
到著頂， at the peak.
with capacity for 210 passengers.
它會減少等待時間，by well over 70%。
The new tramcar will be 33 metres long.
將提供 improved peak tram access for persons with disabilities.
我們有投資超過700萬香港元在這個項目。
We are improving as every aspect of the journey from arrival at the terminus.
In 2018, we transported 6.5 million people on the Peak Tram.
將完全移除的queues從公共區域外邊的下層和上層門檻。
將提供覆蓋、温度控制的Waiting Areas for up to 1,300 people at the lower terminus.
and we will significantly enhance the image of the Peak Tram as one of Hong Kong's most important tourism icons.
If you look at the plan that's on the screen, the arrival will be much more open and will feature a significant piece of public art.
Peak tram upgrade will increase the capacity by 75% from 120 to 210 passengers per trip.
The fifth generation tramcar, the one that we've just taken out of service, was 18.7 metres long and carried 120 passengers.
and an excellent turnout.
of local visitors for the last month.
We will install a wheelchair lifting platform.
with new haulage system and ropes.
and will have access paths from the main entrance.
with a very positive public and media response.
我們正 undergoing 一 total 系統和 infrastructurе upgrade。
strengthen track and bridges, and new stronger rails.
and then they will move after purchasing tickets into a multimedia entertainment experience.
We have planned significant improvements to access for persons with disabilities.
Will provide access ramps from the tramway path to boarding and alighting platforms.
一號第五 Generation tramcars 被移除於6月28日早上。
香港 said farewell to the fifth generation of tramcars on the 27th of June this year.
The new tramcars will have wider doors, which will allow roll-on and roll-off at all eight doors, with wheelchair fixings at each gangway.
There will be an extensive and fascinating historical gallery to entertain our our guests while they are queuing for tickets.
once that is complete, they will move up travellers up to the new platforms, where they will get the first glimpse of the new peak tram.
We are now in our final phase.
remaining strengthening of the bridges and slopes.
replacement of all the rails, pulleys and sleepers.
Upper terminus structural alterations and refurbishment.
And include lower terminus expansion and refurbishment.
The new haulage equipment, which you can see, is massive.
strengthening of the covered nuller under the lower terminus transit area.
installation of haulage equipment, ropes, control and signalling system.
was built and tested in Europe, and has been delivered to Hong Kong.
and the transit area, the lower terminus, and the main entrance.
They went through the Suez Canal on the 9th of August, and are currently sitting outside Djibouti.
We have undertaken extensive demolition, and construction works are ongoing at the former lower terminus.
Our team are in the final stages of removing old rails, and new rails are now being laid on the track.
Our new tramcars were built and tested in Switzerland, and are now being shipped to Hong Kong.
then we will install the new tramcars, which will be tested and commissioned, and the staff will undergo extensive training.
we have the the haulage equipment has now been removed from the Peak Tail haulage room, including haulage drum, gearbox and motors and deflection sheaves.
環節啦，係邊位想提問？
第二個 Suspension， as I've said， commenced on the 28th of June。
We commenced the construction of this project in December 2018.
and our target completion is late December this year.
誒會唔會誒維持不變咧？定係誒其實係收幾多錢咧？噉樣唔該。
and had held our first tram suspension between the 23rd of April and the 22nd of July of 2019.
係呢一個誒纜車嗰個收費㗎啦，咁所以咧其實係由個市場去定價嘅，所以究竟嗰個收費跟住落嚟嘅發展係點樣，我都請翻阿孫生作答嘅，唔該。好啊，阿孫萬天先生。
Thank you very much. Okay, thank you very much. 啊，跟住咧，我係請委員注意咧，立法會曾經成立小組委員會研究二零一八年山頂纜車安全修訂規例。
誒設施嘅咧，咁呢個第一樣首問啦。第二就係除咗纜車公司投資啲七億之外咧，其實政府有冇相應自己都投放一啲資源去配合纜車公司呢一節嘅即係成個發展計劃咧？咁呢個第二個問題。第三咧就係。
呢個附屬嘅《百利志在》咧，修訂纜車車廂嘅定義，並將纜車車廂載客量咧，從最高附載一百二十名嘅乘客咧，增加到二百一十名嘅乘客。委員咧可以參閲小組委員會嘅報告，啊，以瞭解詳情嘅。咁而家我進入提問嘅環。
阿鄭鄭英員啊，鄭英員，你開始先啦。好啊，唔該，主席。誒，正如阿Mr Sawyer頭先講啦，山頂纜車係香港有特別象徵意義嘅一個，即係即係運輸系統啦，所以我係好支持呢次佢嘅發展計劃嘅。咁咧，我有幾個問題想問咧，就係第一咧，我原先睇到文件。
咧就話更新呢次系統咧，嗰個總成本係誒六點五億。但係頭先咧，我見到喺誒呢個最新嘅資料裏邊咧，就話七億。噉我想問誒呢個七億係咪都包括曬所有嘢？不係除咗系統之外啊、車廂啊，所有嘢都包喺度，而且咧係唔需要再添置其他嘅。
誒疫情爆發以嚟咧，其實誒外地嘅遊客數量咧直線下跌，咁照計纜車嗰個營業額都受影響嘅。噉我想問誒，佢呢個計劃應該都有銀行融資㗎，會唔會因為呢個營業額下跌咧，影響到佢喺融資方面誒有問題，從而又倒翻轉咧影響，譬如佢。
佢每次提款個進度誒會唔會對工程有影響咧？咁呢個第三個問題。最後一個問題就係想問誒，根據前一段時間嘅收入咧，山頂纜車個門票收費同原來個預算係咪誒都係有調整咧？如果復業嘅時候呢個誒山頂纜車門券嘅收費咧？
係邊位回應？誒主席，我先答咗誒第誒二條先，就係誒，然後我將第一、第三同埋第四條咧係。好啊，阿鍾偉聰，你先。好啊，請講。其實咧係誒，纜車公司咧，佢哋係會全數承擔發展計劃嘅所牽涉嘅錢嘅，咁所以政府咧冇。
所以就發展計劃咧，出公堂嚇呢個係誒第一樣噉，所以因此咧就話七億究竟裏邊係夠唔夠，包括啲乜嘢嘢嘅話咧，我會請翻阿誒孫生作答嘅。咁另外咧，關於嗰個收費嗰度啦，其實咧我哋喺誒一九八六年咧已經冇再誒用法例咧嚟到控制。
Thank you for the question.
In terms of tickets.
for for for the project.
誒，下一位係姚思榮議員嚇。
In terms of
效果咧噉樣，呢方面誒山上面有冇一啲配套嘅做法？
第二個問題就係誒旅行團方面啦。以往纜車係對旅行團方面有啲特別通道嘅，咁將來誒纜車公司會唔會有對針對旅行團方面有啲特別嘅安排嘅咧？
咁呢個等車等等候區同以往比較咧，誒足唔足夠咧？噉樣啊，如果唔足嘅話嘅話，超過一千三百個嘅話咧，誒，纜車公司有乜嘢嘅誒後備方案，以避免旅客等得太耐咧？
The work required, apart from obviously the ongoing maintenance of the tracks, the trams, the slopes and all of the things that we we have to do on an annual basis anyway, but our investment, as I say, will be definitely in excess of 700 million, but will cover the whole project.
Obviously, as a as a commercial business, we look at all of the factors involved in in the prices that we set for for the peak tram. We look at the market outlook. We look at our profit expectations, our expenses and our investments when when we're planning that fee structure.
which is is much appreciated. The comment was also mentioned public transport and the Peak Tram is not public transport. It's it's recreational. It's a tourist facility. And so we we set fares in a commercial marketplace, looking at the competition as well. Thank you.
If I can respond firstly on the on the investment in the presentation, I said over seven hundred million dollars, and we are still making sure that that we're fully fully funding the project. Once we have complete, as I say, our targets at the end of the year, there will be no further.
Project slippage. I think I think there was a question on project slippage. The project has slipped. Covid has, along with every other business in the world, has affected us significantly. It's affected the suppliers, our supply chain, the manufacture of the trams, the manufacture of the equipment. So, yes, that's definitely affected it, and yes, that's cost us more money.
We we don't have a number today, but as a commercial business, we believe that that our customers will will reflect on on any service that doesn't provide value for money, and will vote with their feet. So there was a comment earlier that that full support for this project was given.
誒多謝主席。誒呢個發展計劃，我相信市民會歡迎嘅，亦有助旅遊業。我哋旅遊業界都會支持嘅嚇。噉啊誒問問幾個問題，一個就係誒按照山頂纜車規劃咧，會有一千三百個候車誒，即係有設施嘅候車誒等候區。
第三個就係誒山下面嘅設施好清楚啦，即係做得比較完善啦，亦增加咗用地。山上面嗰邊會唔會有個配套嘅安排，避免山下面做得好，而山上面咧係做唔到，達到嗰個誒提升嗰個畀人感覺誒好嘅效。
喺誒。
誒。
其他方面嘅準備嘅咧。
誒呢一個啊，係咪誒？
咁呢個係黑的啦。誒，至於嗰個誒。
誒纜車公司做得好，但係其他嘅誒設施做得不足，而造成咗誒旅客或者市民嘅不便咧。
誒第五個問題就係有關嗰個誒將來誒頭先誒有誒藍色公司所講咧，呢個係旅遊項目嚟嘅。
違規嘅情況嘅，誒警方會繼續即係誒採取相關嘅執法行動啦，希望都達到個阻嚇作用，即係阻止呢啲有關嘅即係事情再發生嘅。
仲一個就係個舊車廂啦，誒而家個舊車廂好多市民都係嗰個集體回憶嚟嘅，咁呢個舊車廂有冇考慮誒重置或者誒會點樣處理嘅咧？啊，一共係六個問題。
纜車公司咧就一齊係以往都已經係同佢一個好好嘅合作夥伴咧，係去即係宣傳㗎啦。當然啦，佢誒整好咗做咗嗰個誒優化計劃之後咧，亦都係佢再重開嘅時候咧，亦都係誒會有特別嘅宣傳活動啦，亦都係旅發局會繼續配合嘅嚇。
嚇！呢個或者畀翻呢個誒題目，我不如畀翻阿誒誒誒誒纜車公司答啦，因為其實佢哋處理緊嗰個而家最第五代嗰個車廂嘅嚇嚇。至於誒呢一個誒誒宣傳，咁當然啦，就係話旅發局咧係誒經常都係配合咧呢一個啊。
另一個問題就係關的士管理啦。大家都知道山下面嗰度咧，經常好多啲黑的喺度等候啲客人嘅。噉啊，呢方面誒，我唔知政府或者係誒藍色公司就嗰啲誒黑的嘅管理問題、的士管理問題有冇誒附設嘅一啲安排，避免咧即係話。
噉啊！我都希望政府喺纜車公司即係起好呢個纜車站之後咧，喺其他宣傳方面，政府會唔會增加一啲嘅安排，使到呢個一百三十三年歷史嘅纜車站咧，都能夠起到一個輔助旅遊嘅作用。喺呢方面，政府有冇？
中文嚟嘅先。係誒，主席，不如我答咗黑的嗰個問題，同埋舊車廂嗰個問題先。仲有就係誒政府嗰個宣傳，然後咧關於誒個計劃裏邊嘅其他啲車站可唔可以容納到客嘅咧，我就畀翻阿孫生答。好啊。嗱誒，黑的嗰度咧，其實我哋或者對翻準個麥，我成日聽唔到嘅。
誒政府咧，其實一直都誒知道呢個問題，亦都係致力去打擊嗰個違規嘅行為嘅。我哋知道咧，就係誒花園道誒纜車總站黑的呢個問題咧，其實警方咧就一直都有執法嘅，噉就都誒不時有用放射行動去打擊呢個違。
啊！纜車嗰個舊車廂究竟係點樣安排咧？其實第四代嗰個車廂咧，如果即係議員都會有留意到咧，我哋就已經擺咗喺山頂嗰度咧，係一個旅客嘅服務中心㗎啦。即係嗰個係上一次嘅。咁今次呢一個咧就誒，我而家知道咧就應該係咧誒考慮緊會擠喺。
Thank you.
people in.
Thank you for the question.
好，噉我跟住請翻藍車公司係回答啦，阿孫萬天先生。
Every seven or eight minutes, we won't see a problem at all.
The track, so as when our passengers go up and down, they can see both the the burgundy tram and the the old green tram.
staff for monthly ticket holders and for tours, so there will be a fast track line specifically designated for for different passengers.
A couple of organisations on utilising those trams for various activities. They've requested confidentiality until they can work out how they're going to deal with them.
With the capacity, the capacity of the new trams, we don't see an issue any longer for for queues building up outside the building at all. We believe that the the supply and demand now situation is that that we'll remove that instantly.
I think I sort of answered the question in terms of standards at the peak, the same as as standards at the lower terminus. Clearly, we don't have the same space at the peak tower that we do at the lower terminus. But as I've said.
the the comment I think was the questions on the old trams, the fifth generation trams, as we showed in the photograph, we removed one one tram car which is two compartments, and they have gone into storage. We are in discussions with.
Questions, I should say plural. In terms of the waiting area, quite rightly as you said, we are increasing the capacity to approximately 1,300 people that can wait in temperature-controlled comfort and be entertained. Currently or previously, maybe I should say, we could we could fit about 420
But I think the most important aspect is not about how many people can wait, but about the fact that we can now transport so many more people with the two hundred and ten in the new tram that we don't believe there will be there will be that we believe there will be very little waiting anyway. So so we see no issue in terms of.
Either the lower terminus or the upper terminus at the peak, we believe there will be no queues. Very occasionally on incredibly busy days. Hopefully, when our tourists come back, there may be there may be some queuing, but it will be nothing like before. And we believe with this, the capacity of the trams to move two hundred and ten people.
In terms of access, I think the question was access for tour groups. You're right, we've always had specific access points in the entrance and pass ticketing for tour groups, and that will continue. We will ensure there are fast track lines for both tenants of the peak for our.
But we are actively negotiating with with with a couple of different organisations. The other tramcar with the two compartments is parked next to the old green tramcar, the one thousand, nine hundred and fifty s tramcar that we retained previously, and that will that will stay on next to.
規例。
修訂。
現根據。
雖然好簡單啊！
二零一八年，山頂纜車。
括弧二零一八年第一七一號法律公告，第一條。
咁睇下大家仲有冇其他事項，如果冇咧，我就完成呢個工作啦嚇。多謝大家嚇。
噉我咧就除咗向呢個委員會誒作出口頭報之外咧，亦都有書面報告，亦都會稍後提交嘅。
指定二零二一年十二月十七日為該規例開始實施的日期。好。
誒嗱，因為好簡單，咁大家都冇乜誒特別問題啦。我都想講講嗰個立法時間表嚇。咁嗰個附屬法例審議嘅屆滿日期咧，就係二零二一年嘅九月一號啦。
誒就呢個修訂附屬法例嘅作出預告期限，就五整天嘅，就二零二一年嘅八月廿五號啦。我會將向內務委員會活過期咧，就係八月二十號嘅。
好，就冇其他問題。冇問題。好，如果冇其他問題咧，就我想問一問大家，需唔需要邀請公眾啊就生效日期公告表達意見咧？啊，不需要啦，嗬。O K。好，我哋而家咧就誒政策問題，我哋討論完啦。噉我諗可以進入呢一個條文，喺政府第一帶嗰個個審議條文啊嘛。